<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions on a postscript to the defence of Dr. Sherlock, against the calm discourse of the sober enquirer as also on the letter to a friend concerning that postscript.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7291</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12325439</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12325439</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59536</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25440)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 932:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions on a postscript to the defence of Dr. Sherlock, against the calm discourse of the sober enquirer as also on the letter to a friend concerning that postscript.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [20]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707.</term>
               <term>Trinity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59536:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59536:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS <hi>on a</hi> Poſtſcript <hi>to the Defence of Dr.</hi> Sherlock, <hi>againſt the Calm Diſcourſe of the</hi> Sober Enquirer: <hi>As alſo on the</hi> Letter to a Friend <hi>concerning that</hi> Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>BEFORE I begin them, I ſhall take a little notice of the ſeveral Characters which ſeem to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh each Author.</p>
            <p>THe Doctor, or Dean, or Defender, (no matter which I name, for they Three are One) wants nothing to make him a good Writer, but a good Cauſe, and ſays as much for a bad, as any Man can; nay, and when the Nature of the Cauſe will bear no more, he makes it good with Magiſterial Grace and big Aſſurance. He has always Logick enough by him, to prove a Trinity of Faculties, Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Modes, to be only a Trinity of Names; and a Trinity of Eſſences or Natures, to be a Trinity of Gods. All that can be ſaid of him is, that he takes no care of himſelf, but ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices his own Hypotheſis, to make ſure work with that of his Adverſary.</p>
            <p>His Adverſary the <hi>Enquirer,</hi> ſteps forth from the Preſs, at his firſt Appearance in the Cauſe, with all the winning Civility, and good Nature in the World. He will not be ſo rude as to ſay, that his Hypotheſis is the certain Truth of the Matter; only he hopes that his gentle Reader will be ſo courteous, as to grant it poſſible.</p>
            <p>The Dean would do the Enquirer a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Favour, to let him be now and then of his Opinion; but that being not granted, put him a little out of temper; yet he quickly recovers himſelf, and when he has cut the Dean with a bitter Sarcaſm, <hi>p.</hi> 42. he gives him in a healing Parentheſis, an Anonydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Contradiſtinction.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, this is the Caſe between the Dean and the Enquirer: The one deals rude and heavy Blows; the other neatly offers dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Thruſts. You may fancy them engaging like <hi>AEneas</hi> and <hi>Mezentius</hi> in <hi>Virgil,</hi> who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Fight,</p>
            <q>Hic gladio fidens, hic acer &amp; arduus haſtâ.</q>
            <p>In the firſt Page of the Poſtſcript, I meet with theſe words, — I do not intend to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Book, nor approve or diſprove it; and yet he examin'd the Book, and that not careleſly neither. I have again and again con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd thoſe Words, and perhaps at laſt have ſpelt the juſt Senſe and Meaning of 'em, and yet but part of 'em; for why he ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own intending to examine the Book, that I can't account for, nor perhaps himſelf. When he avows he did not intend to approve the Book, he avows that which is Grammatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59536:2"/>and Literaily true; it never came into his Head, to ſet his Seal to any thing of Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s drawing up. And when he ſays, he did not intend to diſapprove it, that is Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically and Figuratively true: for by the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure call'd <hi>Apophaſis,</hi> a Man denies to do or ſay that which he ſays moſt emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and does moſt induſtriouſly. Having now ſaid thus much, why may not I be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to gueſs at the Reaſon, why the Dean profeſs'd, that he intended not to approve or diſapprove Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Book: poſſibly it might be this; He can patiently endure any Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, to make good the Trinunity, except it be ſuch a ſawcy one, as ſets it ſelf up in competition with his, and would impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take place of it. Now better the Article be loſt, than that the Man, who ſlights the Dean's Undertaking, ſhould ſave it, or that the Church ſhould be beholden for preſerving her Faith entire, to the Wit and Learning of a pitiful Diſſenter.</p>
            <p>The Poſtſcript affirms, that <hi>thô the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirer does not in every particular ſay, what the Dean ſays, yet he ſays what will juſtify the Dean againſt the heavy Charge of Tritheiſm.</hi> The Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeript makes good this Affirmation thus, —<hi>What the Dean ſays of Three diſtinct, eternal, infinite Minds, that Mr.</hi> H. <hi>ſays as plainly, and in more obnoxious Terms.</hi> What a lamentable Argument is this? Will Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s broad Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical Diſcourſe evince that Mr. Dean has not made juſt ſuch another? Will <hi>Clodius</hi>'s Lewdneſs abſolve all the wild Gallants in <hi>Rome?</hi> He that ſets up three Gods, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhews what little Reverence he has for the one true God, though he may chance to find others, who preach and print as perverſly as himſelf, is nevertheleſs a Tritheiſt; their running into the ſame wicked Error, will not at all excuſe him. Again, it is to be noted, that the Dean in charging Mr. <hi>H.</hi> to have uſed more obnoxious Terms than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, [he means more liable to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as implying three Gods] does grant that he himſelf has uſed obnoxious Terms; Terms implying three Gods; then is he more to be blamed than Mr. <hi>H—w:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, though he be an unlucky Tritheiſt, yet does not ſeem to know it; but the Dean profeſſes to know the bad Conſequence of his obnoxious Terms, and yet is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to uſe them.</p>
            <p>The Dean has briefly and fairly recount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what Manner of Repreſentation Mr. <hi>H.</hi> has given of a Trinity in the Godhead, which may be yet more briefly ſet down thus; — <q rend="inline">God can unite two Spirits in as cloſe an Union as Soul and Body, which after their Union ſhall remain diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd by their own individual Eſſences, and diſtinct by their ſingular Eſſences; and if he can thus unite Two, then Three; and if Three, then it muſt be granted poſſible, that Three eternal uncreated Spirits may be united in the Godhead, retaining their ſeveral Diſtinctions, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the cloſe and numerical U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Further, — the Union of the Divine and Humane Nature in one Perſon, is not more conceivable, nor poſſible, than the Union of three diſtinct Eſſences, or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Natures in the Godhead.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now is Mr. Dean, in the Malice of his Heart, for ſending Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> to Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> to know of him if this be not Tritheiſm: But for my part, if I were to die for't, I could find no Difference between them. Three diſtinct Minds or Spirits, and Three diſtinct Eſſences or Natures, with all the Perfections of the Godhead in all and every of them, can be no leſs than three Gods. Yet the Dean is pleaſed to ſay [looking upon Mr. <hi>H.</hi> as a convicted Tritheiſt, without a word to offer for his Hypotheſis] that the Animadverter charges him (the Dean) with Tritheiſm only by conſequence. Bleſs us! how would he be charged? He has had the Luck hitherto, and I hope will have the Wit hereafter, to forbear the aſſerting in plain Terms, that there be Three Gods; but his Hypotheſis plainly implies it, and Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s does no more: and Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> has proved his Charge againſt the Former. No, no, ſays the Dean, for three diſtinct Minds are not three diſtinct Subſtances or Eſſences.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59536:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>No! What are they then? Why, they are three diſtinct thinking Beings: <hi>Defence of Dr.</hi> Sher. <hi>Notion, p.</hi> 86. This Dean may advance what Notions he pleaſes, and never ſtand in fear of any Arguments which can be brought againſt him; for as Mr. <hi>Bays</hi> in the Rehearſal, out-wrote all his envious Brethren, by the help of a <hi>Drama</hi> Common-place-Book, ſo he with the help of an Eccleſiaſtical-Polity Common-place-Book, when he has advanced fooliſh and inconſiſtent Notions, ſhall eaſily reconcile himſelf to himſelf, and make good that Concluſion which beſt ſutes his preſent Purpoſe; or when the worſt comes to the worſt, puzzle the Cauſe, ſave his Honour, [which is all he cares for] and hide his Nonſenſe.</p>
            <p>The Rules of that wonderful Book, are ſaid to be theſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Regula fiduciae,</hi> or the Rule of Aſſurance. This Rule directs him, firſt, in <hi>cauſa ſimplici,</hi> as thus: If the Importunity of Hereticks forces us to find Names for that, to which nothing in Nature anſwers, if they will not give us leave, we muſt take leave to uſe ſuch Names as we can find: <hi>Def. p.</hi> 14. 2dly; It impowers him to cut off the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Horns of a mercileſs <hi>Dilemma,</hi> with a Fore-ſtroak the one, with a Back-ſtroak the other; as thus: If a ſawcy Adverſary charges him with Self-contradiction, he tells him, that it is impoſſible to know what a Contradiction is: and when himſelf charges a Tranſubſtantiating Blockhead with Self-contradiction, then it is poſſible to know what a Contradiction is. <hi>Vindic. of Trin. p.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>His Second Rule is <hi>Regula conſortii,</hi> or the Rule of Company; it may be call'd <hi>Regula recriminationis:</hi> this Rule may have two In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; both which he follows with this one Reſolution, not to be damn'd alone, give him Company and it's another thing: Hence you have him frequently returning Railing for Railing, and he can hardly forbear in open-words the baſe Language of grinning-Dog to Dr. <hi>S—th; Def. p.</hi> 39. He does give it him by Rhetorical Inſinuation; and when he has made his Adverſaries Opinion appear as abſurd as his own, he thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſafe; for why may not he have the luck to be thought in the Right, when they that oppoſe him cannot mend the Matter? Thus when Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> tells him, that Three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Minds are Three diſtinct Subſtances: he replies, that according to the received Definition of a Perſon, [which is, <hi>Subſtantia individua naturae rationatis</hi>] Three Perſons are Three diſtinct Subſtances; and let the Doctor bring off Three Perſons, he will do as much for Three Minds: <hi>Def. p.</hi> 89. And thus he diſputes, and is too hard for all that own the Athanaſian-Creed, and explain the Myſtery otherwiſe than he does: If (ſaith he) every diſtinct Perſon in the Trinity, be not a diſtinct infinite eternal Mind, there's an end of the Dean's Notion; but then there will be an end of a Trinity of Divine Perſons alſo, and we ſhall have nothing left but a Trinity of Modes, Poſtures, Names. <hi>Def. p.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>His Third Rule is <hi>Regula perſonae,</hi> or the Rule of Diſguiſe: By this Rule he winds and turns things as he pleaſes; ſhows how things are true, and how falſe; and how neither true nor falſe. For example; when he had never a good material Image of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nothing but a faint Reſemblance or two of it; he ſays that the proper and natural Signification of Words cannot reach the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; a Theological Uſe of words perhaps may repreſent it; <hi>Def. p.</hi> 13. and to prove the Trinity, they muſt be forc'd to uſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper Words in unnatural Significations: for, ſays he, the Names of Diſtinction in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary uſe, not only diſtinguiſh, but divide and ſeparate their Subjects; but in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the word <hi>Perſon</hi> is us'd in the Senſe of Diſtinction, and not of Separation, <hi>i. e.</hi> in a ſenſleſs Senſe, in a Senſe whereof we have no Idea, in an impoſſible Senſe, or to ſpeak fully, in the Dean's Senſe. A <hi>Trinunity,</hi> in the proper Signification of Words, is a Figment; in the improper, an Article of Faith. But
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59536:3"/>now for <hi>un' coup Maltre</hi> to diſguiſe all, perhaps 'tis nor Figment, nor Article of Faith; for in his <hi>Vindicat. of the Trinit.</hi> p. 4. he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that he neither underſtands, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the thing whereof he ſpeaks: and if he don't, no Body elſe does, that's cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; ſo then 'tis to no purpoſe to diſpute the Controverſy, but 'tis direct madneſs to fault his Explication.</p>
            <p>His Fourth Rule, is <hi>Regula Meioſios,</hi> or the Rule of Extenuation, and leſſening the Matter, when it looks groſs, and like an overgrown Monſter. Thus he pleads, that his new Divinity may not diſguſt his Reader: Cuſtom indeed has not made the Form of his Expreſſions Orthodox, but they have no Heretical Senſe in them. Again, Tho the living Image is the ſame Man with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totype; yet 'tis no mortal Sin againſt Logic, and common Senſe, to ſay that a Man, and his living Image, are two diſtinct Men. <hi>Def. p.</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>His Fifth Rule, is <hi>Regula Suppoſitorum,</hi> or the Rule of putting Caſes; not ſuch as the Gentlemen of the <hi>Timple</hi> put, which have happen'd, and may do ſo again, but of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Caſes which never did, never can hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. This is a ſingular Rule, and of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite uſe: for let him coin a Notion, like which there is nothing in all Nature, ſuch as the natural Unity of mutual Conſciouſneſs; why, 'tis but ſuppoſing an impoſſible Caſe, and the airy Notion is as eaſily convey'd to your Mind as you could wiſh. <hi>Def. p.</hi> 33. O the wonderful Virtue of an impoſſible Caſe ſuppos'd, to convey the true meaning of an incomprehenſible Myſtery to the Mind of a Man! Again thus, He ſuppoſes a Man, with a living ſubſtantial perfect Image of himſelf; which living ſubſtantial perfect Image of himſelf, is but the very ſame Man as himſelf; tho ſometimes perhaps they may be two Men, <hi>i. e.</hi> when they don't a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. <hi>Dif. p.</hi> 31. Once more, He ſuppoſes a Beaſt to be a Perſon; not that he thought the Expreſſion proper, but only by way of Alluſion, and Accommodation, the better to repreſent the Union of Two Natures into One Perſon, which are Two Perſons, or ſomething as like Two Perſons, as their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures will permit them, when they ſubſiſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. <hi>Def. p.</hi> 46. What if I ſhould put an idle Caſe, Had I this Man's Deanery, could not I talk as wiſely?</p>
            <p>His Sixth Rule, is <hi>Regula Tenebrarum,</hi> or the Rule of darkning the Matter. Thus having often granted, that the whole Divine Eſſence was in the Father, and in the Son, and in the Holy Ghoſt; to prevent the Conſequence, that then there are Three Divine Eſſences, he carefully diſtinguiſhes and tells his Reader, that the whole Divine Eſſence ſubſiſts thrice, not by multiplying, but by repeating it ſelf. There's a Vail thrown over the Matter now; and where's the Man that has that Eagle's, or Epidauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Serpent's Eye as to pierce through it? But after all, I could wiſh, that he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore this Diſtinction, for hence may ariſe a knotty Queſtion, which may give Poſterity much trouble, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether a Sinner that repeats his Injuſtice, Intemperance, and Lying, may be ſaid to multiply his Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? or whether all is but one Fault, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting often by frequent repetition?</p>
            <p>He has many darkning Dictinctions, ſome in common with his Trinitarian Friends and Enemies, ſuch as Creation, Generation, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; other peculiar to himſelf, ſuch as 'tis one thing to conſider a Perſon diſtinctly and by himſelf, another to conſider him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parately and apart: but for a thick cloudy one, you ſhall not meet with one more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable than this, The Divine Nature is one individual Nature, but not one ſingle Nature. <hi>Def. p.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>I come now to his laſt Rule, which indeed and in truth, is no Rule; but he uſes it ſo frequently, one might imagine it was his main Rule: conſider it ſeparately, and apart
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59536:3"/>from the reſt, and it is plain that it is no Rule of his; but conſider it diſtinctly, and you'l find that it is a Rule to him, ay, and that more proper words could not have been thought on to repreſent it, for it is call'd <hi>Regula obliviſcentiae,</hi> or the Rule of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs. By this Rule, without bluſhing, he tells Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> that three diſtinct Minds, are three diſtinct thinking Beings, not three diſtinct Subſtances; <hi>Def. p.</hi> 89. tho <hi>p.</hi> 19. he had diſputed againſt the Being of but one ſingle Divine Nature in the Godhead, quoted and conſented with <hi>Victorinus Aſer,</hi> that 'tis not lawful to ſay there is but one Subſtance. Thus alſo, <hi>p.</hi> 26. he ſays, that he does pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly teach, that each of the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons has entirely all the Perfections of the Divine Nature, Divine Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs; and therefore each of them is an eternal infinite Mind, diſtinct from each other: tho he had ſaid, <hi>p.</hi> 26. that neither the Son, nor Holy Ghoſt, was an abſolute, compleat, independent God; and yet one would think, the Perſon that has all the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the Godhead, ſhould be a perfect God. 'Twere eaſy to give more Inſtances of his practice of the Rule of Forgetfulneſs; but I will not foreſtal Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> I only take leave to obſerve, that it is a very ſhameful Practice, and not to be indur'd in any Man but the Dean; but in him it may be indur'd, becauſe he can ſhade it by the Rule of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Rule the Sixth; or alter the Looks of it, by the Rule of Diſguiſe, Rule the Third; or throw the diſgrace of it upon his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, by the Rule of Company, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination, Rule the Second; or prove it no ſhameful Practice, by the Rule of putting Caſes, Rule the Fifth; or take off from the Odiouſneſs of it, by the Rule of Extenuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rule the Fourth: and if none of all theſe help him in his Diſtreſs, he has his firſt Rule, the Rule of Aſſurance, which is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; by which he will outface the Matter, <hi>in re malâ, animo ſi utare bono, juvat, ut nihil ſuprà.</hi> But after all theſe helpful Rules of his Eccleſiaſtical-Polity Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place-Book, as a Friend, I would adviſe him to conſider, whether he be concern'd in that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy; If any Man teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, and conſent not to wholeſom Words, even the Words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the Doctrine which is according to Godlineſs: He is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about Queſtions and ſtrifes of Words, whereof cometh Envy, Strife, Railings, evil Surmiſings.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Upon the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Strife of Words, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus</hi> notes, <hi>quod Interpres Graecus dixerit</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which, but for the tried and known Loyalty and Orthodoxy of the Dean, I would render ſeditious Reaſonings.</p>
            <p>To return from this long Digreſſion, if ſuch it be; for though it is off from the <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> yet not altogether beſide the Matter. The Dean juſtly and truly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, that Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Three Spirits, and Eſſences, and Individual Natures, which make up the Unity of the Godhead, as he has repreſented it, do not ſeem to be Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite: for, that which Three become by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united, not any one of them can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be, conſider'd by himſelf: If each cannot be conſider'd by himſelf, then the Three cannot be diſtinguiſh'd; if each can be conſider'd by himſelf, each muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd as not wholly the ſame with all the Three in Union. But the Dean forgetfully, and untruly ſays, that he allows but One Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, and One individual Nature; for, [not to take notice of that pitiful Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, One Divine Nature repeated in Three Perſons without Multiplication] <hi>P.</hi> 91. of his <hi>Self-Defence,</hi> he has theſe expreſs words, <hi>The Dean knows no Divine Subſtance, or Eſſence, diſtinct from the three Divine Perſons, but that the Eſſence makes the Perſon.</hi> What he means by the Eſſence makes the Perſon, I do not well know; but 'tis moſt manifeſt, that if a Divine Eſſence, and a Divine Perſon, be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59536:4"/>the ſame without diſtinction, that then there are as many Eſſences as Perſons, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as Eſſences, nor more nor leſs. In my mind, Three Divine Eſſences, are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by two; he had better loſe two Perſons, than be overſtor'd with Divine Eſſences; for one Divine Eſſence, and one Divine Perſon, is enough for any truly honeſt and religious Man.</p>
            <p>When the Dean declares, that to own Three Eſſerces, and Three individual Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the Godhead, without making Three Gods, ſeems to have ſome Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: methinks he ſeems to fear, Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: methinks he ſeems to fear, that the ſame may be ſaid of his Three Minds. But as I have above noted, Three ſingle Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he can admit of, and they will go for Three individual Eſſences, with any Man that has a thinking Mind, and no myſterious By-cauſe to ſerve.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> having ſaid, in his <hi>Sober Enquiry,</hi> that the Dean's Hypotheſis left out the very <hi>Nexus,</hi> that ſhould unite the Three Perſons, and that mutual Conſciouſneſs between Two or Three Spirits, will not conſtitute them one Thing. The Dean anſwers him with ſtudied Reſpect to his <hi>Rule of Diſguiſe; Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Conſciouſneſs</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is not a Mutual Inſpection, or Inſight into one another, but a feeling each other in themſelves.</hi> But for my part, I hate a Diſguiſe; and therefore I will make as bold with him, as he with the Unitarians; and if he will not give me leave, I will take leave to pull it off.</p>
            <p>Mutual Conſciouſneſs (ſays he) is not a Mutual Perſpection, or Inſight into another, but a Feeling each other in themſelves. Now I will prove, that it is both a Seeing, and Feeling, nay, and a knowing too each other in themſelves. <hi>Def. p.</hi> 73. <q rend="inline">Perſons eſſentially one by Mutual Conſciouſneſs, do ſee, and know, and feel each other in themſelves, as every ſingle indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Mind ſeels its own Thoughts and Paſſions.</q> If the Dean will except againſt this Author, there's an End of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but, I think, he has more Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for him than ſo. Now by this which I have here obſerv'd, I do ſee, and feel, and know, that the Dean's ſtudy is not to frame an Anſwer to his Adverſary's Objection, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to his firſt Explanation of his bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Terms; but to ſay what is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be ſaid, for the putting by a preſſing unmannerly Objection, whether it agree with his Explanation or not. And then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain it is worth noting, he is pleaſed to call, <hi>a Feeling each other in themſelves,</hi> (by which he defines Mutual Conſciouſneſs) an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal vital Senſation. Now Senſation will take in <hi>Seeing,</hi> as well as <hi>Feeling;</hi> and then Mutual Conſciouſneſs, if he keeps to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, will be <hi>Knowing</hi> each other in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. In ſhort, <hi>Seeing, Feeling, Knowing</hi> each other in themſelves, are Forms of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, which he uſes promiſcuouſly; not very Orthodox indeed, but there is no He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Senſe under them; no Senſe at all that I know of: but as he complements Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> they are <hi>Gipſy-Cant.</hi> Hold, I cry him Mercy, for Gipſies underſtand one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Gibberiſh. His <hi>not very Orthodox Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions,</hi> may perhaps be better call'd Roſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crucian Cant; for that myſterious Order of Philoſophers, are the only Perſons that I know of, beſides our groſs Tritheiſts, who uſe Words without any intelligible mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Mutual Conſciouſneſs, is really nothing but a ſhameſul Inſtance of the Dean's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in putting impoſſible Caſes, which it were not difficult to expoſe; but his way is, to eaſe his Adverſary of that Labour, and do it himſelf. His Self-Conſciouſneſs refutes his Mutual Conſciouſneſs, <hi>i.e.</hi> if he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin'd them aright; for how ſhould he, that by Self-Conſciouſneſs feels himſelf to be himſelf, by Mutual-Conſciouſneſs, feel him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be ſome Body elſe? It is true, an intelligible Senſe of theſe words may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: As thus, I am conſcious to my ſelf of what I think, ſay, or do; and what is known to me and my Friend, of that we two are mutually conſcious: But the Dean never underſtands words in their proper and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſignification, is never contented, till
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59536:4"/>he has made them ſignify, what no Body can underſtand, nor he declare without talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backward and forward, ſo ſhamefully, that were it not for fear of his Vindictive Spirit, every Man would do as Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> has done, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſhow him his Picture, I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid, his <hi>living</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial Image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he is ſure that Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> can never form any Notion of the Union of Spiritual Eſſences, without Mutual Conſciouſneſs. It muſt be his Prejudice then that hinders him, for Spiritual Eſſences may be united by Conſent; but that's not the Union he intends, he intends an Eſſential Union, and that's an Eſſential Contradiction, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Nonſenſe.</p>
            <p>The Dean fairly recounts, that Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> repreſents the Unity of the Godhead, by the Union of Soul and Body, which make one Man; and by the Union of the Divine and Humane Nature, which are ſaid to make one Chriſt. Now he criticiſes, and affirms theſe to be Perſonal Unions, [meaning Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of divers things, which make one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon] but cannot be the Unity of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, in which there is a Trinity of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Perſons. I know no inconvenience of allowing according to common Acceptation, that Soul and Body make up one thing, call'd Man; nor know I what Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> can get by it, for neither of the two ſingly is Man; or if each of them ſingly is ſo, together they muſt make up a double Man: Which was the Fancy of the ſilly Indian in <hi>John Dreyden</hi>'s Play.</p>
            <q>
               <l>I kill'd a double Man, the one half lay</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Ground, the other ran away.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But the Dean rejects theſe Unions, (he ſays) becauſe they are not the Unions of diſtinct Perſons. But that is not fair, for he himſelf has confeſs'd, once and again, that there is nothing in Nature like Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in One Godhead: And I muſt take leave to tell him, that if there were, Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> is as like to find it as he: But ſince there is not, they muſt e'en both be content with ſuch faint Reſemblances as they can get. As for the Union of two Natures, I have a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Reaſon for rejecting than the Dean by much, it is building Myſtery upon Myſtery, and proving one Dream by the help of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Unity of the Godhead is ſuch, and no other, than the Dean ſpeaks it; ſuch an Union of Three Spiritual Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Individual Natures, as together [which is fairly call'd, by Compoſition] conſtitute the Godhead. Againſt this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ſays ſome things weakly; thoſe the Letter takes notice of, and perhaps I may alſo ſpend my Verdict on them there: other things he ſays well, and with ſound Reaſon, but in them he is moſt unlucky; for inſtead of Three Spiritual Beings, Three Individual Natures, read Three Minds, or Perſons; and his Arguments conclude equally againſt his own Hypotheſis. In ſhort, what he ſays well, comes to this; If all Three are but One God, then not any One by himſelf is that One God: and this he ſays Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> has own'd, <hi>p.</hi> 47. and I think his words come near it, which are theſe; <hi>When you predicate Godhead of any One of the Perſons, you expreſs an inadequate Conception of God.</hi> But to prove himſelf a ſounder Trinitarian, he ſays that he owns, and that none are Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Chriſtians but they who own ſo too, that the Father has the whole entire Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in himſelf, that the ſame ſubſiſts in the Son, the ſame in the Holy Ghoſt; that each by himſelf in the moſt proper adequate Conception, is true and perfect God, tho all Three are but One and the ſame God; which does plainly and undeniably prove, that the Dean, and all his Orthodox Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do believe, that the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are One and Three, in one and the ſame reſpect. For that Godhead, which by them is <hi>predicated</hi> of every of the Three ſeparately, that very Godhead is <hi>predicated</hi> of the whole Three conjunctly.</p>
            <p>The Dean ſays, that Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Notion of the Unity of the Godhead, is ſuch, that neither the Scriptures, nor the Antient
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59536:5"/>Church know any thing of it. I am of the Mind, that the Scriptures know as much of the Hypotheſis of one of them, as of that of the other: and as for the Antient Church, who can tell what he means by it? the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers beyond the acknowledg'd Rules of good Life, neither agree with one another, nor any one with himſelf; but I gueſs his Antient Church to be made up of thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Doctors whom he judges to have talk'd his Way, though I won't ſware but they may have drop'd a word or two in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Divine Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Where any late Socinian Writers have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd themſelves willing to compound this Diſpute of a Trinity of Divine Perſons, for the Three Attributes of <hi>Power, Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> I know not. I beg the Dean's pardon if I wrong him, when I believe he wrongs them: for I obſerve that they have noted that there are other as eſſential Attributes of God, as the Three mention'd, <hi>viz. Truth,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and ſo the Myſtery will conſiſt of five Parts; and that is two more than it did, when it had two too-many. And then if any of the Trinitarians make but an Attribute of the H. Ghoſt, yet they all do and muſt allow Jeſus Chriſt to be a Perſon, and they all do affirm him to be one, and the ſame God with the Father, which I am very ſure the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians will by no means agree to. Indeed when the Trinitarians explain the Trinity, by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling God as the Creator, <hi>Father;</hi> as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, <hi>Son;</hi> as Sanctifier, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> the Socinians ſay, for Peace ſake they can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure this; but then they alſo ſay, 'tis a harſh Way of ſpeaking, and in my Judgment, off from the Queſtion: for ſuppoſe that ſome Trinitarians could part with the perſonal Deity of the Holy Ghoſt, yet they are all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinaciouſly zealous for this impoſſible Piece of the Myſtery, that Jeſus Chriſt is one and the ſame God with his eternal Father; and then, though they may perhaps ſometimes think good to ſhelter themſelves under the Proſeſſion of One God, for various Reaſons variouſly denominated, yet they cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Controverſy about Three Perſons, for Three Attributes. Jeſus Chriſt is a Perſon, and I think they all make him one in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and they may as well make three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be one God as two, and as well ſome other number as three.</p>
            <p>The Dean egregiouſly miſtakes one thing, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Socinians are afraid of the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis of Three Divine Perſons, each of which is God: but I will aſſure him 'tis no ſuch thing; though they are aſham'd of it, 'tis ſo infinitely abſurd, and manifeſtly impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, they need not be afraid of it; for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will never recommend it, only Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may fright them from examining it, who were bred up to it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>On Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Letter in reply to the Poſtſcript.</head>
            <head type="sub">Nec quenquam jam ferre poteſt Caeſárve priorem, Pompeiuſve parem. —</head>
            <p>Could <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> have agreed to ſhare Empire between them, they might have manag'd <hi>Rome,</hi> and the World as they pleas'd: but <hi>Pompey</hi> proud of his early Fame, and long Proſperity, would needs be uppermoſt, while <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Succeſs againſt the Gauls prompted him to endure no Superiour: ſo they divided their Intereſts; the Event was, <hi>Caeſar</hi> was too hard for <hi>Pompey</hi> by his Valour, <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59536:5"/>by their Treachery too hard for <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would Mr. <hi>H—w,</hi> and Dean <hi>Sherlock</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to ſhare the Honour of explaining the myſterious Doctrine of the Trinity between them, it would be a great ſtroke towards perſwading Church-men and Diſſenters to Orthodox Tritheiſm; but as ill-luck will have it, to the Prejudice of every <hi>Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes,</hi> whether of Church or Tabernacle, the Dean is pertinacious for his Hypotheſis, <hi>there muſt be Three diſtinct Minds in one Numerical Godhead, or no Trinity:</hi> and Mr. <hi>H—w,</hi> that could be contented to have his Scheme ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted as poſſible, cannot endure to have it ſet by, as Hereſy. So they expoſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ſcoffing Railery of Theiſts, and Atheiſts, to the Scandal of weak, and to the Contempt of wiſe and good Men. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears on the Dean's part from what I have ſaid in my Examination of his Poſtſcript, and will appear from what I have to ſay on Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Letter. Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> reduces the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute between him and the Dean, to theſe two Heads: 1. Whether the Enquirer has ſaid more than the Dean, or more than is defenſible of the Diſtinction of the ſacred Three in the Godhead. 2. Whether the Dean hath ſaid ſo much as the Enquirer, or ſo much as was requiſite of their Union. Of the firſt, I affirm they have both ſaid more than is defenſible: there is indeed ſome Difference in the Sound of their Terms, but their Senſe on both Sides is equally Abſurd and Tritheiſtical.</p>
            <p>Three Minds and Spirits, Three Eſſences and individual Natures; if every of them is ſuppos'd to have all Divine Perfections, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of them is ſuppos'd to be a True God, and all of them to be Three Gods. One and the ſame is the Hypotheſis of theſe two angry Writers, only varigated with different Terms of Art. They catch, and cavil at one another, for ſome little By-ſayings or Omiſſions, but return not one wiſe word to the plain Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherewith they condemn one another for Tritheiſts.</p>
            <p>They are mutually ſelf-conſcious of their Pagan Error, and that ſuppreſſes the Pride of their Hearts: ſo when they fain would raiſe their Voices to a triumphal <hi>Jö,</hi> all they can reach is, <hi>I will vindicate Three Minds from being Three Gods, as well as you Three Natures; and I will aſſert Three Natures to be but One God, as well as you Three Minds.</hi> Before I read Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Letter, I could not have imagin'd that he would have rivall'd his inſolent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary in this weak Abſurdity; but I ſee an indefenſible Cauſe will ſhame a Man of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Parts, and high Provocation put a calm Enquirer beſide his Temper: For thus, <hi>p.</hi> the 7th, Mr. <hi>H—w,</hi> denying the Charge of having expreſly ſaid, and extenuating his having implied, that the ſacred Three are Three diſtinct Subſtances, is content with this ſorry Reply; — <hi>There is ſomewhat more conſiderable in the Notion of Subſtance, according whereto, if the Dean can make a ſhift to avoid the having of any inconvenient thing prov'd upon him by conſequence, I hope the Enquirer may find a Way to eſcape as well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> never roſe above hoping well of his Hypotheſis: here he ſeems to deſpair, and the myſterious Article may go where it will, if his Honour be but as ſafe as the Dean's: Indeed it is a reaſonable Deſire to eſcape but as well as the Dean, and it is ill luck if he does not; yet I believe he is not like to eſcape much better neither.</p>
            <p>The Dean in his Self-defence takes the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to affirm, that he allows but one Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, one Individual Nature in the Godhead: Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> is content to intimate, that he believes the Dean has ſaid the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his Vindication; I am ſure on't, and ſhall make bold to point to one notorious Place, it is <hi>p.</hi> 47. there he teaches, that <hi>the Divine Perſons are ſubſtantial Beings; and that if each Perſon be God, each Perſon has a real Being, a real Nature and Eſſence of his own.</hi> This is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough a conſcience: Three diſtinct Perſons with each his real Nature, muſt needs make Three real Natures; and if each Perſon is God, each Nature is God [for 'tis the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Nature which conſtitutes the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon] and then there be three Natures,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59536:6"/>which three Natures are three Gods.</p>
            <p>To the Dean profeſſing to own but one Divine Eſſence, Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> ſlightly objects, that the contrary appears from his Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metaphyfical Fancy, upon that Paſſage; —<hi>The Son is the expreſs Image of his Father:</hi> for the Dean deſcants that the Image, and the Prototype muſt be diſtinct, and two in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and he illuſtrates it, by the Similitude of the Man, and his living Image, which muſt needs make two Men, if there be ſuch a thing as a living Image of a Man; and if there be not, who can help it? 'tis no fault of his: And after all, may not an impoſſible Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition (to uſe Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Phraſe), though it does not come to the Matter, yet <hi>ſerve to free our Minds, and diſentangle them from being under a neceſſity to conceive things to be, after ſuch a manner, as will be found to differ nothing from Socinian Hereſy?</hi> But enough of the Dean's nauſeous Nonſenſical Meraphyſicks.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> ſpares the Dean upon his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between one individual Nature, and one ſingle Nature, only throws him one Pun to confound him; if the Divine Nature be not a ſingle Nature, it muſt be a double, a triple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then concludes fairly, that the Dean has aſſerted Three Divine Natures, unleſs all ordinary forms of Speech muſt be abandon'd and forſaken: and I will be bound to diſpute this Cauſe with either of them; ay, and let them change the ordinary forms of Speech, (of which the one is as guilty as the other) provided they will define their new Forms, and in their Diſcourſe keep to their own Definitions.</p>
            <p>As Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> tells the Dean, if the Divine Nature is not a ſingle, then 'tis a double, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo I tell him, if the Divine Nature is not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is compound, and ſo the Dean and he may ſhake Hands. But Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> deſires it may be noted, that there is this great Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between him and the Dean: The Dean ſpeaks poſitively, dogmatically and proudly; whereas he (Mr. <hi>H.</hi>) does but ſuppoſe what he ſays as poſſible, not certain [the two laſt words had been better omitted]; and by the way, for him to endeavour to prove his Hypotheſis poſſible, is to ſuppoſe it uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. Well, 'tis granted, there is ſuch a ſort of Difference between him and the Dean; Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> has a Paſſion for the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, Mr. Dean for his Expoſition of it: Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> does what he can to make out the Matter, he would give any thing it were made out; ay, though it were by his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, he hopes it will be made out, though he is afraid not by himſelf: but the Dean poſitively affirms, that the Doctrine is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true after his particular Manner; and he ridicules all his Brethren, who, being equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd for it, would take up with any lower ſort of Trinity than a Trinity of Three diſtinct Minds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 13. Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> comes to examine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Dean has ſaid as much for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Unity of the Godhead, as himſelf, the Enquirer: and he rightly notes, all that the Dean has ſaid is Mutual-conſciouſneſs; but what he ſuppoſes againſt its Sufficiency to ſalve the Unity of the Godhead, is as weak as the Dean could wiſh.</p>
            <p>Three intelligent Perſons (as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues) muſt be pre-united before they can have vital Perception of one another's Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations: But the Dean ſuppoſes the Three Perſons in the Trinity eternally united, and eternally Self-conſcious; that indeed is as wild a Suppoſal, as a Viſionair can make: but the Dean is us'd to ſuppoſe impoſſible things, and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> not us'd to argue well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>Mutual-conſciouſneſs will never come up to do ſervice, and credit the Trinitarians common Dream of Eſſential Union: for ſhould we ſuppoſe that Three diſtinct, intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Spirits are conſcious to one another's Thoughts, yet they will ſtill remain Three diſtinct intelligent Spirits, and not one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Spirit: their Knowledg of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and perfect Harmony, will come to no more than a Socinian Unity, an Unity of Agreement, a knowing and willing the ſame things: and ſo far as I ſee, the Doctor's Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis is not pure from Hereſy, for all his Three Gods.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59536:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 16. Mr. <hi>H</hi>— comes to conſider over again his own way of maintaining the Unity of the Godhead, and to defend it againſt the Dean: but firſt he premiſes, what I muſt reflect upon; he ſays, the Dean's Temper of Mind, in what he writes <hi>p.</hi> 105, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſuch, that no Man, whoſe Mind is not in the ſame Diſorder, will apprehend any thing in it, but ſuch Heat as dwells in Darkneſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> deviliſh Heat. Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s Calmneſs is not ſo ſenſleſly dull, as to oblige him to die in the Dean's Debt: This was a rude Stroke; but in the next Line he ſtabs him with a clean and artificial Sarcaſm. The Dean had gracefully began his Letter thus; True, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom reſts not on an ill-natur'd and perverſe Spirit; I underſtand it, (ſays <hi>H—w</hi>) while the ill Fit laſts: So <hi>Joab</hi> hugg'd <hi>Abner,</hi> when he ſmote him under the fifth Rib: This was enough a Conſcience, Mr. <hi>H</hi>— needed not have wonder'd that the Dean could write that excellent Saying without Self-reflection. So <hi>Ovid</hi> ſpoil'd <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia pontus erat,</hi> with <hi>deerant quoque littora Ponto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 17. Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> ſpeaks thus: <q rend="inline">The thing to be reveng'd is, that the Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer did freely ſpeak his Thoughts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he judg'd the Dean's Hypotheſis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective; his not taking notice of what he reckon'd naturally Antecedent, and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental to Mutual Conſciouſneſs; a moſt intimate, natural, neceſſary, eternal U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Sacred Three.</q> Now it is true, that it is not ſafe to make too bold with the Dean or his Hypotheſis; <hi>nemo illum impunè.</hi> But if a Man ſhall find fault with him, who takes as little Care as the Dean, to write nothing amiſs, he muſt expect to be ill us'd; and to ſay the truth, he deſerves it.</p>
            <p>But what is that which the Dean ſhould have taken notice of, and did not? Why, <hi>the intimate, natural, neceſſary, eternal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Sacred Three.</hi> Now I am of the mind, that the Dean looks upon his Mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs, as <hi>the</hi> intimate, natural, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, eternal Union: according to him the Sacred Three ever were, and could not but be thus united; and therefore they might again ſhake Hands, if there were nothing but the Philoſophy of the Myſtery between them: But ſince they will not be Friends, I that am a ſtander by will ſee fair Play.</p>
            <p>It ſeems the Dean had objected, that the Enquirer repreſents the Unity of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Soul and Body,</hi> and <hi>by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Divine and Humane Nature,</hi> &amp;c. Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> confeſſes he partly does ſo, but more fully by the ſuppoſed Union of Three created Spirits. Now if ever Mer, that pretended to Reaſon, diſcours'd more ſenſeleſly than both the one and the other of theſe Diſputants, they ſhall burn me for an Heretic. They both confeſs, that there is no exact Repreſentation, no perfect Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of any ſuch Union in Nature; and yet they will be repreſenting it, over and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again; ſometimes by a Tree and its Branches, ſometimes by the Sun and its Light, ſometimes by a Mind and its Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſometimes by Body and Soul: and that nothing may be wanting in <hi>them</hi> toward; the repreſentation of it, they repreſent it at length by that which is not; an Eſſential Union of a Divine and Humane Nature, and by a ſuppoſed Union of Three diſtinct crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Spirits.</p>
            <p>The Dean, as I have above noted, has told us that the proper and natural Signification of Words, will not reach the Myſtery: Then if he were not very much at leiſure, he would not make words about it; for his Readers muſt judg of what he writes, by the proper and natural ſignification of his words, or be content to be ignorant of his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for he has not, and I gueſs will not, publiſh an Engliſh Gloſſary, to ſettle his improper, unnatural ſignification of Words; which he calls alſo <hi>Theological Signification,</hi> as being content to let words go for what they us'd to do, except in Church-Matters and Myſteries.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> has once and again cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd us to forbear determining what is, or is not in God, beyond what God hath
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59536:7"/>plainly told us in his Word, or made our own Faculties plainly tell us: Yet does this Man labour to perſwade us, that Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Three Natures may be in God, tho nor God, nor our Faculties have plainly told us ſo, by ſuppoſitions of things, which he himſelf thinks only poſſible, dares not ſay are Actual and Real; and if they were not only Poſſible, but Actual and Real, are yet confeſſedly below the Matter, not able to repreſent it, much leſs to prove it. But after all, his grand Suppoſition is as impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible as any of the Dean's, who allows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſuppoſe what neither is, nor can be, when Reaſon fails him to credit his Fancies; for a Spirit, and a Spirit, and a Spirit, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one diſtinct, cannot poſſibly become but one Spirit, if he means by <hi>Spirit</hi> the ſame thing all along; but if he takes the <hi>Subject,</hi> in this Enunciation, in the proper and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſignification of the Word, and the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate</hi> in the improper, unnatural, Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Signification, then I confeſs Three may be as few, One may be as many as he pleaſes. I have heard, in Table-talk, (I cannot ſay have read) that the late famous Dr. <hi>More,</hi> makes it part of the Definition of Religion, that it be competently obſcure; let Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> and the Dean alone for mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good this part of the Definition; if they have not (by their Spirits and Minds, Self and Mutual Conſcious, by their Three, diſtinct, without ſeparation; their One, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual, without ſingularity; by their Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Natures, coexiſtent in one Eſſence or Nature, while each of the Coexiſtents is that ſelf-ſame One, which all of the Coexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtents are together, by their State of Real and Vital Union, with continuing Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;) made it obſcure enough, then I know not, what thoſe words <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>obſcure</hi> mean. I am perſwaded that neither of theſe Writers can flatter himſelf ſo far, as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that his printed Hypotheſis, has gain'd one Proſelyte, or confirm'd one wavering Trinitarian; I can aſſure them, they have both ſcandaliz'd and loſt ſeveral thorow Trutarians; and I have Reaſon to think, that the Unitarian late Tracts, would not have been half ſo much enquir'd after, if the Trinitarian Writers, by their abſurd and contradictious Explications, had not ſhock'd and unſettled the Minds of many honeſt Chriſtians, who were bred up to the Article, and out of Reverence to Authority, took it upon truſt, without any manner of examination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 19. The Dean profeſſes, that, as far as he can underſtand, no other Union will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy the Enquirer, but ſuch an Union of Three Spiritual Beings, and Individual Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as by their Compoſition conſtitute the God head, as the Compoſition of Soul and Body does the Man. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> reſents this as a wilful Injury, and ſays, the Dean has a croſs Underſtanding, (which may be true, but not for what Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> complains of) for he aſſures his Reader, that he has peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denied all Compoſition in the Godhead; and it is true, he has, <hi>in terminis,</hi> deny'd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the Godhead: But then again it is as true, he has in plain Synonimous words affirm'd the very thing. Both Mr. <hi>H—</hi> and the Dean have afferted that to be in the Godhead, which Compoſition doth properly and naturally ſignify: but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what it does improperly, unnatural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and theologically ſignify, they have both denied Compoſition in the Godhead; ſo that neither the one nor the other of them is an Heretic, but in a proper and natural true way of ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>But now behold an odd Scene: While the Dean objects thoſe very Opinions as Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors to Mr. <hi>H</hi>—, which the Dean has after his own way himſelf profeſs'd: Mr. <hi>H</hi>— ſummons all his Art, to deny the Charge which he is not willing to deny, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Doctrine which he is not willing to own: Of which I will give Inſtance, when I have firſt ſet the Matter even between them, concerning <hi>Simplicity</hi> and <hi>Compoſition.</hi> Mr. <hi>H</hi>— has diſputed earneſtly againſt the Univerſal, Abſolute, Omnimodous Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the Divine Nature. Againſt it alſo has the Dean ſtrenuouſly reaſon'd, and it's
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59536:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>manifeſt that Three Self-conſciouſly diſtinct, Mutual-conſciouſly united Minds, are as far from Omnimodous Simplicity, have as much of Compoſition, as Three diſtinct Natures eternally, vitally united. The plain Truth, which with abundance of Theological Stuff, theſe Learned Barterers diſguiſe, is this God's Simplicity, is his Singularity, his U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Eſſence, or Nature. If there be more Eſſences than One in the Godhead, then the Godhead is not Simple but Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound: But if God is but One Eſſence, or Nature, then he is <hi>ſummè Simplex;</hi> which I would Engliſh, truly Simple, or Single, or One: but that one Thing, or Perſon, ſhould be more Simple, Single, One, than another; that is a by-whim of Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s a good Mantling for a ridiculous 'Scutcheon. It does not contradict the Simplicity, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, Unity of any Being, that it has ſeveral Excellences, and divers Powers of acting. Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s talk of Simplicity, which excludes Modes, is pure Banter and Amuſement: The Simplicity, and Singula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his own Perſon is ſtill the ſame, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the different Figures which he makes, when he is preaching a plain, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, uſeful Sermon, at <hi>Pinners Hall;</hi> and when he is penning and publiſhing calm Diſcourſes, and vindictive Vindication Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The Dean objects, that Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> will not endure Wiſdom, Power, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to be the ſame thing in God. Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> thinks himſelf civil, for not giving him the Lie: He makes bold to tell him, it is not fairly ſaid; and here it is that he uſes his Art in denying and admitting the Charge; ſo that 'tis impoſſible for the Reader to find out his Senſe of the Matter. As an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it was not fairly ſaid by the Dean, he declares, that he only intimated, we are not inſtructed in Scripture, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs</hi> in the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, to be the ſame thing; and that our Difficulty is great to apprehend them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinguiſhable. Now I note, that if it be difficult to apprehend them undiſtinguiſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then he ſeems to judg them really un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinguiſhable, tho 'tis difficult to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them ſo. But the Dean knowing Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> able to ſee through a Difficulty, ought not to have charg'd him, with holding them to be divers Things; but then preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, this forgetful Man, ſays, 'tis a great Weakneſs of underſtanding to define them alike. If they cannot be defin'd alike, then they are really diſtinguiſhable; and if he thinks them truly defin'd, when they are deſin'd differently, then he cannot poſſibly apprehend them undiſtinguiſhable; and then the Dean has dealt fairly, and the croſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is Mr. <hi>H—w</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>The Dean urges that Mr. <hi>H</hi>— by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Power, Wiſdom, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs prepar'd his way to make a natural Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in Unity of them: In truth, any Man might have gueſs'd ſo as well as the Dean; But the Enquirer tells us, his Diſcourſe was never intended to terminate in ſuch a Trinity, tho it ſeems plauſible, or not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd. It is a great Fall from <hi>poſſible</hi> to <hi>not abſurd;</hi> and then, that it only ſeems not abſurd, is another great Fall. Why did Mr. <hi>H</hi>— concern himſelf with ſuch an Hypotheſis, an Hypotheſis of ſo ill a Nature? Why, he did it to diſentangle Mens Minds from an apprehended neceſſity of conceiving the Three Attributes to be One and the ſame Thing. A Propoſition that only <hi>ſeems,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not abſurd, is no very fine Argument to diſentangle Mens Minds from Error: but, to let that paſs; who are they that apprehend a Neceſſity of conceiving the Three Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to be One and the ſame Thing? Not the Unitarians, he knows it, none that ever wrote; for he challenges the Dean to name that Writer, that does not diſtinguiſh them, at leaſt <hi>ratione ratiocinatâ,</hi> in contradiſtinction to <hi>ratiocinate:</hi> let him no more than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face his Diſcourſe with this natural Trinity in Unity, unleſs he deſigns to diſentangle the Dean's Mind with it; and if ſo, let him make his beſt on't. Upon his Succeſs, I will promiſe him <hi>Egregiam laudem, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; memorabile nomen;</hi> He cannot get much more by freeing the Doctrine of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59536:8"/>the Trinity, from the Difficulties in which it is entangled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 26. Mr. <hi>H—w</hi> teaches that the Son is from the Father by neceſſary eternal Proma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the Holy Spirit from Father and Son; and that the Three moſt celebrated Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, [though I know not why Truth and Juſtice ſhould not be celebrated as much as they] are neceſſary Emanations, con-natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to their Original.</p>
            <p>Now all this muſt be taken in the unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, improper, theological Meaning of the Words; which what it is, none but the Sons of Art know, and 'tis againſt their Rule to make it common. But from the proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Meaning of the Words, the Wit of Man cannot make out an intelligible agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Propoſition. If Mr. <hi>H.</hi> thinks other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, let him try, and define what <hi>Promana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is, what <hi>Emanation,</hi> what <hi>Proceſſion,</hi> &amp;c. if he has any Idea in his Mind of what thoſe Words ſignify, he may deſine them: if he has no ſuch Idea, then let him confeſs himſelf beholding to the Dean, who teaches a puzzled Trinitarian, to reſt his Terms up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Theological Bottom. But methinks the People are very hardly us'd, when they are requir'd to believe Myſteries, which will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure no Explanation, but in Words that are to be taken in a Senſe which neither they can find out, nor will their Teachers tell them. But I recal my ſelf, I think the People are not put to ſuch hard Terms of Communion, but Preachers only; nay, whether they are or no, I am not poſitively certain, for <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſint,</hi> may be as well interpreted <hi>cum grano ſalis</hi> in this Matter, as it is generally in ſome other; and as for the damnatory Clauſe at the End of one odd Creed, very few are of that ſtrong Stomach, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Temper, as not to be ſick and aſham'd of it.</p>
            <p>In the three next Leaves I meet with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but barbarous Stuff about Compoſition between the two Antagoniſts. On which all I ſhall note, is, that the Dean puts a word or two out of joint, which is no great matter in ſuch a perplext Diſpute; and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> falls upon that, and thence takes occaſion to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlook the Intention and Force of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary's Argument.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H. p.</hi> 33. brings in the Dean diſputing againſt the Hypotheſis of Three diſtinct Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences, Natures, Minds, Spirits, neceſſarily and eternally united in the Divine Being, after this manner; — <hi>God is eternal, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made; but whatever has Three ſuch Eſſences in it, muſt have a Maker.</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is the leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for this Argument, becauſe it does the Dean's Buſineſs as well as his; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for the Cauſe more than the Dean, and therefore he will rub it off as well as he can; and ſo he defies the Dean to prove, that there is any Inconſiſtency between a Thing's having Three diſtinct Eſſences natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and neceſſarily united in it, and its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eternal and unmade. To this the Dean might anſwer, [whether conſonant to his Hypotheſis or no, that troubles not me, nor perhaps, when he comes to anſwer, will it affect him] Be it granted, that the Terms <hi>naturally</hi> and <hi>neceſſarily united</hi> are not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with thoſe other, <hi>eternal</hi> and <hi>unmade:</hi> for <hi>Wiſdom, Power</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> [I will add] Juſtice and Truth, are naturally and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily united in God, and alſo eternal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made; but then Three diſtinct Eſſences can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be naturally and neceſſarily united, and yet eternal and unmade: becauſe the Maker of all things is one Eſſence, one ſingle Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and cannot poſſibly conſiſt of Three diſtinct Eſſences, which is Compoſition; and that appears, becauſe the Three diſtinct Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences muſt either be ſuppos'd every of them <hi>God,</hi> in an adequate Senſe, or only in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adequate Senſe. Three diſtinct Eſſences, each of which is God, in an adequate Senſe, are without Contradiction, Three Gods: and Three diſtinct Eſſences, two of which are God only in an inadequate Senſe, are in a juſt and true Senſe, leſs than God; and what is leſs than God, cannot be eſſentially united to him, but does depend upon him, and was made by him. If there can be ſuch Things as Three diſtinct Eſſences naturally and neceſſarily united, they muſt then, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59536:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Dean ſaid, have a Maker, and muſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in Union, from what they were in Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as the <hi>Whole</hi> does from a <hi>Part,</hi> or elſe muſt be one and three, three and one, in one and the ſame reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 34, and 35. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſtrives not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Dean, which he ought not to do, becauſe the Dean is ſo oft not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, let who will ſtrive to underſtand him; but Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is to be excus'd, becauſe that which he is not willing to underſtand, he is not able to anſwer. In ſhort, all that I ſhall here offer, is, if Mr. <hi>H.</hi> determines that every of the Three Perſons in his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, are adequately, compleatly, fully, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly God, then it is plain, that his Trinity is a Trinity not of Perſons only, but of Gods alſo; and if he determines that no one by himſelf, but all Three together are perfect God, then his Three Perſons and Natures, are no better nor worſe but the Parts of a Compoſition as the Dean calls them; and finite Parts [as all things muſt be called, whereof no one is perfect God] will never make an infinite Compoſition: which Truth, though very obvious, came not into my Mind till I read a Paper of that great Man's, the Author of the Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 36. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> will not admit that the Three Perſons are of a different Kind, or Nature, but that they differ only in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; that is, as much as to ſay, that they are all Three eternal, which <hi>in terminis</hi> was too abſurd for the Zeal of the Author of the Athanaſian Creed, [ſo I muſt call it, for <hi>Athan.</hi> has Sins enough of his own to account for.]</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is now pleas'd to mend an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Dean's, and then it runs thus; <q rend="inline"> Though we have a natural Notion of an eternal Being, we have no Notion of Three eternal Eſſences which neceſſarily co-exiſt in an eternal Union.</q> To this he replies; — <hi>Does he</hi> (the Dean) <hi>mean, that we are to disbelieve every thing of God, whereof we have not a natural Notion?</hi> No, no, no, it is enough, good Mr. <hi>H.</hi> enough for him to mean, that we are not requir'd by God, nor ought to be by Man, to believe any thing whereof we have not a natural Notion. But Mr. <hi>H.</hi> pleads, that his Notion is moſt favour'd by Divine Revelation: And is that all? with what Conſcience then can he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Article to be Fundamental, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be believ'd, when the moſt that he can ſay for it is, That his Notion thereof is moſt favour'd by Divine Revelation? Nay, and at the ſame time, other Expoſitors are as ready to pretend, that the Scripture fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours their Expoſition more than Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s. Let me be allow'd one ſhort Digreſſion; —I dare venture my Life on't, that the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians ſhall unanimouſly come into the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the Doctrine of Three Perſons in One God, if but a Majority of Church-men and Diſſenters ſhall agree upon the Signification of the Terms, and publiſh that one Senſe of the Article, which they (the Majority) dare profeſs to believe: but if a Majority of them are not like to come to ſuch an Agreement, and perhaps not the Tithe of them are, then let them either Chriſtianly indulge the Unitarians in their contrary Perſwaſion, or Honeſtly tell the World, that they hold it neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to believe Words, the true and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Senſe of which they judg cannot cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be determin'd.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>H.</hi> intimates, that againſt his Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis, favour'd by Scripture, there is no evident natural Notion: What ſays the Dean to this? why he argues to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; If there be Three Spiritual Beings, of diſtinct Natures in the Godhead, no One of them can be abſolutely perfect and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; becauſe they are not the ſame, and no One of them is the whole. Here now is an evident natural Notion againſt his Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis: to which he replies, 1ſt. By way of Conceſſion; that it is an Argument of ſome Strength: But, 2dly, it reſolves it ſelf into the Notion of <hi>Infinity,</hi> about which he ſpake his Senſe to Dr. <hi>Wallis;</hi> and 'tis worth the while to know what that Senſe was, <hi>viz. That he will not move, nor meddle with any Controverſy about the Infinity of the Three ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59536:9"/>Subſtances, or Spirits in the Godhead;</hi> i. e. he ſpoke his Senſe of it, by declaring he would ſay nothing about it; he ſpoke his Senſe, by his Silence. 3dly, To the Dean, he now begins to ſpeak his Senſe, by ſaying ſomething; what that is ſhall be conſider'd.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing he offers is, from his old Topic of entangling his Adverſary with as puzzling Difficulties as himſelf is entangled by him; — he can give any Man as much Trouble about the Infinity of quantitative Extention, as the Dean can give him about the Infinity of Three diſtinct Beings, which are but one Infinite Being. Well! for once ſuppoſe it: but then I ask, why, why ſhould any Man be requir'd to believe that, which (to uſe his Phraſe) gives him ſo much Trouble; and after all his Trouble, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make to appear indiſputably poſſible? 2. The Infinity of quantitative Extention is an unjuſtifiable Phraſe; for as <hi>Cudworth</hi> will tell him, <hi>p.</hi> 643, 644. <hi>Body</hi> or <hi>Matter</hi> is <hi>indeſinite;</hi> you cannot conceive it ſo great, but you may conceive it greater; but 'tis not poſitively and actually <hi>infinite,</hi> as God is, his Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſo great, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be conceived greater. 3. Though we have not an adequate and fully commenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Knowledg of the Nature of Matter, yet we are certain that contradictory Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning it, cannot be both true; and ſo we are alſo certain, that contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Affirmations concerning the Nature of the Godhead, cannot be both true. 4. Mr. <hi>H</hi>'s Hypotheſis does ſuppoſe contradictory Affirmations; for it ſuppoſes Three perfect Beings, each of which is God; and that theſe Three perfect Beings are but One per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Being, and but One God; and 'gainſt this the Dean argues well.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing he offers is, that he thinks it demonſtrable that One Infinite can never be from another by voluntary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction; by neceſſary Emanation he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes it may. I note; If one Infinite can be from another, (by what Way ſoever) then there may be more Infinites than One; and further, neceſſary Emanation is a Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Phraſe, by which, nor Mr. <hi>H.</hi> nor any Trinitarian elſe, can tell us what is to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay that neceſſary Emanation is <hi>Gipſy Cant,</hi> as the Dean pronounces of ſome Words of Doctor <hi>S—th,</hi> not underſtanding his own groſs Raillery; for Gipſy Cant is intelligible Stuff under uncouth Terms, which is more than the Dean meant to allow to Dr. <hi>S—th</hi>'s words; but I think I may truly call <hi>neceſſary Emanation</hi> perfect Banter; for 'tis an Amuſing Phraſe, that will not endure to be explain'd, and will only ſerve to ſatisfy an implicit Believer, who can be contented that ſomething is ſaid for the Article without conſidering whether it be intelligible, or only empty words, Noiſe and no more.</p>
            <p>Neceſſary Emanation, though a Chriſtian Theological Phraſe, is really very Heatheniſh Stuff. What Emanation ordinarily ſignifies, that we know; but relating to the Godhead, it ſeems it muſt ſignify ſomething elſe; ſo the Blood that flows from one of <hi>Homer</hi>'s wounded Deities is not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: they eat like Mortals, but their Food is not good Fleſh and Fiſh, but <hi>Ambroſia;</hi> they drink too, but not <hi>Burgundy,</hi> but <hi>Nectar.</hi> There is a Difference alſo 'twixt their Gate and ours; for <hi>Statius</hi> tells us, they fetch greater Steps than we, or as <hi>Heliodorus Aethiop. l.</hi> 3. they fetch no Steps at all, but ſweep along: <hi>Aeneas</hi> knew his Mother from a common Mortal Gipſy by that Token.</p>
            <p>I am willing to allow the Enquirer, the Character of a Calm and Modeſt Man, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that he, now and then, lets his Adverſary know, he is no Stoic. He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears very deſirous to be thought Modeſt; Nay, even when he is deſending his Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis with the beſt Arguments his Wit can deviſe, he has ſomething of the Pyrrhonian Sceptic in him. He will not conſidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, nor poſitively ſay, things are ſo and ſo, as he has ſet them: but Zeal to a Cauſe will, one time or other, ſhow its go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Power; witneſs <hi>p.</hi> 39. where he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures to affirm, that we are plainly told
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59536:9"/>by the Divine Oracles of a Sacred Three, that are each of them God. Whereas the Holy Ghoſt is no where called God, the Son but in a few places; and in thoſe few, the Scope of the Writer ſuggeſts to us the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that Appellation, <hi>viz.</hi> the Dignity and Power beſtowed on him by the Father. For which reaſon alſo <hi>Moſes, Solomon,</hi> and others are dignified with the ſame honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Appellation.</p>
            <p>Plainly told of Three, that are each of them God] <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>! How hard a thing is it, when a Man is engag'd, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſerve a Cauſe, to make a Conſcience of what he affirms? We are indeed, as he truly notes, plainly told of Three, and ſome things are ſpoken of each, which cannot be truly ſpoken of all; but this only proves, that the Three cannot be eſſentially the ſame; ſo that if any One of them be truly God, the other two muſt be Creatures. Mr. <hi>H</hi>— is ſtrangely raſh to affirm, that the Scripture plainly tells us of Three diſtinct Perſons, each of which is God; for had that been true, this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy had never been.</p>
            <p>It is, as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> judges, eaſier to count Three, than to determine of Infiniteneſs: But then how bold is he, to determine of the One as he does, and how unlucky is he in count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the other? for he determines that each of the Three diſtinct Perſons are the Infinite God, [ſometimes perhaps he uſes abating Expreſſions]; and he counts God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God the Son, God the Holy Ghoſt, for One God.</p>
            <p>The Dean had argued, that <hi>if all Three Perſons by Compoſition are but one God, neither of them, by himſelf, is true and perfect God.</hi> Which invidious Conſequence he charges Mr. <hi>H</hi>— to have own'd. Mr. <hi>H</hi>— replies, that this is moſt untruly ſaid, and that for his part, he denies both <hi>Antecedent,</hi> and <hi>Conſequent</hi> too. If Mr. <hi>H</hi>— can indulge himſelf to deny in one place, what he has affirm'd in another, he ſhall always have ſomething to ſay for himſelf, whatſoever is ſaid againſt him: but the Dean's Charge was honeſt, for <hi>Calm Diſc. p.</hi> 47. Mr. <hi>H</hi>— writes thus: <hi>Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, being ſuppos'd neceſſarily exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent in this united State, they cannot but be God.</hi> Inſtead now of <hi>Compoſition,</hi> put in the word <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> in the Dean's Argument, and then ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mr. <hi>H</hi>— will not be ſo hardy as to deny the <hi>Antecedent;</hi> and ſtill the Conſequence holds, witneſs the good Man's next words: <hi>When you predieate Godhead, or the Name of God, of any One of them, you expreſs an inadequate Conception of God.</hi> And pray, what is that, but a half Conception of God, a Conception ſhort of what God is? Indeed Mr. <hi>H</hi>— did put in another Epither, and with that his Phraſe ſounds thus: A true, but inadequate Conception. But that is a Contradiction in Terms, for a true Conception of a thing, is an adequate full Conception of it, and an inadequate Conception is not a true One.</p>
            <p>What follows, <hi>p.</hi> 41, and 42. is nothing but a ſenſleſs Stir concerning a Similitude of the Trinity, which they both have us'd, and both confeſs'd nothing to the purpoſe. Mr. <hi>H</hi>— ſays, He brought the Union of Soul and Body, not to illuſtrate <hi>Perſonal</hi> Union, but <hi>Eſſential;</hi> and yet his Buſineſs was to prove it poſſible, that Three Perſons might become one God. So then by his Confeſſion, when he was to prove his Point, he talk'd off from the Matter, as many a fluent Orator has done, that he might not loſe, but puzzle the Cauſe, and ſo ſave it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 42. Mr. <hi>H</hi>— plays upon the Dean with ſcoffing Sarcaſms: But to his Argument re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns nothing but plain dull Falſhood, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Theological Banter.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. He ſays, that the Dean (to make out ſomething againſt him) foiſts in a Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which never came into any Man's Head, but a Socinian's, and his own. This is by a Rhetorical <hi>Hendiadis</hi> to call him a Socinian, as if the Dean had wrote his Vindication of the Trinity to no purpoſe: But herein Mr. <hi>H</hi>— does him manifeſt wrong, for on my Conſcience, he is no Socinian now, whatever he may have been formerly. But Mr. <hi>H</hi>— has a Plaiſter for the Wound which that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59536:10"/>gives: He ſaid what he ſaid [if we will believe him] contradiſtinguiſhing the Dean to the Socinians, that ſo it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more ſtrange that the Dean ſhould foiſt in a Socinian Suppoſition. Thus the Dean is excus'd from being a Socinian, and to mend the Matter, ſet out for a Man of no Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; who being, in truth, an Anti-Socinian, yet argues againſt Mr. <hi>H</hi>—, by virtue of a Socinian Suppoſition, and that <hi>foiſted</hi> in too, Mr. <hi>H</hi>— will not bate him a jot of being a Foiſter. I ſee the <hi>Calm Enquirer</hi> is no Angel, for he brings againſt the Dean a railing Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, which is more than <hi>Michael</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Devil, a worſe Creature than Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> by a great deal.</p>
            <p>Come we now to the Suppoſition it ſelf, ſaid to be foiſted, <hi>If God be a Perſon, he can be but One.</hi> Now this Socinian Suppoſition, or Argument, or whatever it be, does not look like a very unreaſonable One; and if the Dean ſhould be aſhamed of it, becauſe it is ſaid to be Socinian, he may for the ſame Reaſon be aſhamed of the moſt unexceptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable things which he ever wrote. But where's the Foiſting? If Mr. <hi>H.</hi> did not ſay that God was a Perſon, may not the Dean ſuppoſe it, and argue from it? Dares Mr. <hi>H.</hi> deny it? Indeed he dares, but with as emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, metaphyſical Pretence, as can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd. <hi>The Name of God</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is the Name of the Eſſence, not the diſtinguiſhing Name of a Perſon.</hi> This is perfect Theological Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, empty Words, to which he cannot fix an intelligible Meaning: But if Perſon ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify an intelligent Being, as both theſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſts admit, then the Eſſence, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God, cannot be diſtinguiſh'd, but are of the ſame Import; then the Name of God is the Name of that Perſon, or Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Being, which is God. And if God be but one God, then there is but one Perſon, or Intelligent Being, which is God.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H.</hi> purſues his Reaſoning thus: <q rend="inline">If Three Intelligent Natures be united in one Deity, each will be Perſons,</q> [he ſhould have ſaid a Perſon] <q rend="inline">and each will be God, and all will be one God.</q> I grant it, for, <hi>Dato uno abſurdo ſequuntur mille. Let me try my skill:</hi> If Three Intelligent Natures may be united in One, then Two may be ſo united, and then the Dean will be Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> the Dean, each will be a Trinitarian, and both will be one Trinitarian: The truth is, nor Three, nor Two Intelligent Natures can be united into One the ſame Intelligent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Nor can Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and the Dean be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited into the ſame Man; they come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed cloſe up to one another, and are toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Ears, but they can never be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into One.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>H.</hi> thinks it makes for him, tho I know not which way, that he hath, as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines commonly do, ſtil'd the Father <hi>Fons Trinitatis.</hi> What is the Theological Senſe of that Phraſe, I am not able to ſay; the plain Senſe is, that a Trinity of Gods flow from the Father, and Three and One makes Four, unleſs ſome other Myſtery forbid.</p>
            <p>To avoid the Dean's rallying his Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> refers to what he has plainly ſaid of the Order of Priority, and Poſterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>Calm Diſ. p.</hi> 48.</p>
            <p>But not a word has he there ſaid, more than that his Hypotheſis preſerves the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Priority and Poſteriority, not of Time, but of Nature.</p>
            <p>Priority and Poſteriority, with reſpect to Time or Dignity, is intelligible; but Prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Nature, is a bantering Theological Term, incapable of Definition.</p>
            <p>After this Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſays ſeveral things, pinching enough againſt the Dean, but to ſave himſelf not a Syllable.</p>
            <p>I am weary of cenſuring his weak De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and mean to take notice of but one Error more, but that is a notorious one. <hi>P.</hi> 48. he ſays, <hi>That neceſſity of Exiſtence, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the Sacred Three, will prove each of them to be God; and the ſame belonging to the Three, in the Order of Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> i. e. in the Order of <hi>Nature</hi> before-mention'd, proves them neceſſarily <hi>to be one God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That neceſſity of Exiſtence, proves the neceſſarily exiſtent Being to be God, is moſt certain; for that being which does neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59536:10"/>exiſt, has always exiſted: And that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which has always exiſted, had its Being from no other. From that Being, which has its Being from no other, all other Beings muſt have their Being, with all the Powers and Faculties which relate to it: So that the Self-exiſtent Being muſt needs be God, the Great Creator. But now, that neceſſary Exiſtence can belong to Three diſtinct Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, let it be in what Order it will, that's utterly impoſſible: for if Three diſtinct Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings exiſt neceſſarily, then ſuch Three have always exiſted: If they have always exiſted, they have done ſo, with equal or unequal Power.</p>
            <p>Of Three that exiſt with equal Power, no one has Infinite Power. Three, whoſe Power is Finite, have what they have from another. Beings that have what they have from another, do not neceſſarily exiſt.</p>
            <p>Of Three that exiſt with unequal Power, the two that have leſs than Infinite Power, have, what they have, from another, and therefore do not neceſſarily exiſt. But if neceſſary Exiſtence could belong to Three, would that prove the Three to be but One? Then Contraries ſhall prove one another, and both Parts of a Contradiction be true at the ſame time: If neceſſary Exiſtence can prove Three diſtinct Beings to be but One, it may as well prove One to be None. But Mr. <hi>H.</hi> lays ſome ſtreſs upon Self-Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence's belonging to Three in the <hi>Order of Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is this Order of Nature, that can work ſuch a Miracle? Let's conſider. By belonging to the Three, in the Order of Nature, he muſt mean belonging to them altogether, or belonging to them one after another, or not belonging to them at all: If he means belonging to them altogether, then his Order of Nature, is cloſe Order; and proves the Three are One, becauſe they ſhare and ſhare like, in neceſſary Exiſtence: if he means belonging to them one after another, then his Order of Nature is looſe Order, and proves that the Three are One becauſe they take their Turns in poſſeſſing neceſſary Exiſtence: if he means not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them at all, then his Order of Nature is no Order, [which I gueſs is what it will come to] and proves that the Three are One neceſſary Exiſtent, becauſe no One of them does neceſſarily exiſt.</p>
            <p>Not to take my leave abruptly of theſe Trinitarian Antagoniſts, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and Dean <hi>Sherlock,</hi> two Learned Men, but who are not content to know concerning God what plain Reaſon, and clear Revelation tells them; but, prying further into his Nature, pretend that they diſcover Three Minds, Three Spirits, the One of which is not the other; Three Natures, Three Eſſences, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from one another: I ſhall offer a Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Story. —</p>
            <p>They ſay that <hi>Pentheus</hi> having a Mind to diſcover the ſecret Rites of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> got up into a high Tree which overlook'd the ſhady Vale, where the mad Crew were ſacrificing; but they diſcover'd him, and the angry God ſtrook him with Madneſs: Unhappy <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi>'s Madneſs was of that Sort, that all things appear'd double to him; he thought he ſaw two Suns, and two <hi>Thebes;</hi> ſo that, as he was making towards the one, of a ſudden the other appear'd to him, and oblig'd him to change his courſe towards that: Thus poor deluded Man was he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried up and down, to and fro, but ne'r could recover his Town of <hi>Thebes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Learned and Noble Mythologiſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies this inſtructive Fable, to the Reproof of thoſe Men who dream of Myſteries, and by their admirable Skill in Philoſophy nicely expound them. Vain Philoſophy is the tall Tree which they climb to pry into the Divine Nature; ſober Men note their Folly and deſpiſe them, and God gives them up to the Deluſions of their vain Minds, while they diſtinguiſh between the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Divine Light, and oppoſe them one againſt the other: Theſe are the two Suns, and the two <hi>Thebes,</hi> which draw them now one way, now another, and make them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59536:11"/>of uncertain Judgments, always wavering. Now this is their Hypotheſis, now that; now they are confident of it, and now they doubt; now they mend it, and by and by unmend it again. <hi>Hine fit</hi> [ſays my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor] <hi>ut neſciant quo ſe vertant, ſed de ſummâ rerum incerti, &amp; fluctuantes, tantum ſubitis mentis impulſibus, in ſingulis circumagantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>BOOKS lately printed for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Brief Hiſtory of the Unitarians, in Four Letters. Second Edition.</item>
               <item>Defence of the Brief Hiſtory, againſt Dr. <hi>Sherlock.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Acts of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> with Notes on his Creed: and Obſervations on Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Vindication of the Bleſſed Trinity.</item>
               <item>Some Thoughts on Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Vindication.</item>
               <item>Impartial Account of the Word <hi>Myſtery,</hi> as it is taken in the Holy Scripture.</item>
               <item>Letter of Reſolution concerning the Trinity.</item>
               <item>Two Letters touching the Trinity and Incarnation.</item>
               <item>The Trinitarian Scheme of Religion, with Notes thereupon: which Notes contain alſo the Unitarian Scheme.</item>
               <item>Obſervations on Four Letters of Dr. <hi>J. Wallis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Accurate Examination of the principal Texts, alledged for the Doctrines of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of our Saviour, and the Satisfaction. In anſwer to Mr. <hi>Milbourn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Reflections on Two Diſcourſes by <hi>Monſieur Lamoth,</hi> concerning the Divinity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</item>
               <item>Conſiderations on the Explications of the Trinity by Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations on the Explications of the Doctrine of the Trinity. Occaſioned by Four Sermons preached by his Grace the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> A Sermon preached by the Lord-Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> A Diſcourſe by the Lord-Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury.</hi> A Sheet by a very Learned Hand, containing Twenty eight Propoſitions. A Treatiſe by an Eminent Diſſenting Miniſter, being <hi>A Calm Diſcourſe concerning the Poſſibility of a Trinity,</hi> And a Book in anſwer to the Animadverſions on Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Vindication of the Trinity.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:59536:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
